Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 34: The Preterm Newborn.
Respiratory Distress Syndrome Necrotizing Enterocolitis Retinopathy Of Prematurity Brain Disorders Intracranial Hemorrhage Cerebral Palsy References At the time of this textbook’s first edition in 1903, preterm delivery was often followed by neonatal death.
However, subsequent scientific innovation has advanced the threshold of viability to 22 to 24 weeks’ gestation .
Moreover, the overall survival rate for preterm neonates <29 weeks’ gestation approaches 80 percent .
Still, the preterm newborn is susceptible to many serious medical complications both early and later in life .
Table 34-1.
Complications of Prematurity The complications of prematurity can be serious, and this is reflected in overall neonatal mortality rates.
In 2018, two thirds of all infant deaths in the United States were in the 10 percent born before 37 weeks (Ely, 2020; Hamilton, 2021).
Fortunately, rates of preterm birth have declined from approximately 12 percent in 2007 to 10 percent in 2020.
The rate of early preterm births (<34 weeks’ gestation) declined from 2.77 to 2.69 percent, which is the lowest level reported since 2007 .
Respiratory Distress Syndrome.
The seminal complication of the preterm newborn is respiratory distress syndrome (RDS).
This results from immature lungs that are unable to sustain necessary oxygenation due to surfactant deficiency.
The resulting hypoxia can be associated with pulmonary hypertension and neurologic damage such as cerebral palsy.
In addition, hyperoxia, a side effect of RDS treatment, contributes to other preterm morbidities including bronchopulmonary dysplasia, necrotizing enterocolitis, periventricular leukomalacia, and retinopathy of prematurity.
# Etiopathogenesis.
To provide blood gas exchange immediately following delivery, the lungs must rapidly fill with air while being cleared of fluid.
Concurrently, pulmonary arterial blood flow must rise.
Although some of the fluid is expelled as the chest is compressed during vaginal delivery, most is absorbed through the pulmonary lymphatics via complex mechanisms described in Chapter 32 (p. 586).
Sufficient surfactant, synthesized by type II pneumocytes, is essential to stabilize the air-expanded alveoli.
This lipoprotein lowers surface tension and thereby prevents lung collapse during expiration .
If surfactant is inadequate, hyaline membranes form in the distal bronchioles and alveoli, and RDS develops.
Although RDS is generally a disease of preterm neonates, it can develop in term newborns, especially with sepsis, pneumonia, or meconium aspiration.
In these cases, surfactant can be inactivated by inflammation and/or the presence of meconium .
With inadequate surfactant, alveoli are unstable and collapse with the low pressures of end expiration.
Pneumocyte nutrition is compromised by hypoxia and systemic hypotension.
Partial persistence of the fetal circulation may lead to pulmonary hypertension and a relative right-to-left shunt.
Eventually, alveolar cells undergo ischemic necrosis.
When oxygen therapy is initiated, the pulmonary vascular bed dilates, and the shunt reverses.
Protein-filled fluid leaks into the alveolar ducts, and the cells lining the ducts slough.
Hyaline membranes composed of fibrin-rich protein and cellular debris line the dilated alveoli and terminal bronchioles.
The epithelium underlying the membrane becomes necrotic.
At autopsy, with histological staining of lung tissue with hematoxylin-eosin, these membranes appear amorphous and eosinophilic, like hyaline cartilage.
Because of this, respiratory distress syndrome is also termed hyaline membrane disease.
# Clinical Course.
In typical RDS, tachypnea develops, the chest wall retracts, and expiration is accompanied by nostril flaring and by grunting—in an attempt to provide a positive end-expiratory pressure to prevent lung collapse.
Shunting of blood through nonventilated lung contributes to hypoxemia and to metabolic and respiratory acidosis.
Poor peripheral circulation and systemic hypotension may be evident.
The typical
chest radiograph shows a diffuse reticulogranular infiltrate and an air-filled tracheobronchial tree—air bronchograms .
Figure 34-1.
Chest radiograph of a preterm newborn with moderate respiratory distress syndrome.
Note the diffuse granularity throughout the lungs and mild, central, air bronchograms.
The lungs are only eight ribs expanded despite mechanical ventilation.
Respiratory insufficiency can also be caused by sepsis, pneumonia, meconium aspiration, pneumothorax, persistent fetal circulation, heart failure, and congenital malformations involving thoracic structures, such as diaphragmatic hernia .
Common mutations in surfactant protein production and the phospholipid transporter (ABCA3) are rare causes of RDS .
# Treatment.
An important factor influencing survival is neonatal intensive care.
Although hypoxemia prompts application of supplemental oxygen, excess oxygen can damage the pulmonary epithelium, retina, and other immature tissues.
Despite this, advances in mechanical ventilation technology have improved neonatal survival rates.
For example, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) prevents the collapse of unstable alveoli.
This allows high concentrations of inspired oxygen to be reduced, thereby minimizing its toxicity.
To help limit the need for tracheal intubation and intermittent positive-pressure ventilation, CPAP has been studied in well-designed trials (Morley, 2008; SUPPORT Study Group, 2010b).
An initial CPAP strategy coupled with subsequent selective surfactant use is a beneficial alternative to immediate intubation and surfactant for neonates of extremely early gestational age .
Less-invasive surfactant administration techniques allow surfactant delivery while maintaining the preterm newborn on CPAP.
Such methods reduce the need for intubation and mechanical ventilation in the first 72 hours and decrease rates of death or bronchopulmonary dysplasia .
Mechanical ventilation has undoubtedly improved survival rates, but it is an important factor in the genesis of chronic lung disease of prematurity— bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD).
Namely, mechanical ventilation places a newborn at risk for barotrauma and volutrauma.
Moreover, hyperoxia can create reactive oxygen species that trigger inflammation.
Infection also can be contributory.
In affected newborns, alveolar and pulmonary vascular development is disrupted, leading to hypoxia, hypercarbia, and chronic oxygen dependence.
It can also affect adult lung function (Thébaud, 2019).
BPD remains the most frequent complication of extreme preterm birth .
High-frequency oscillatory ventilation is an alternative to conventional mechanical ventilation for preterm newborns.
However, benefits and risks vary considerably between studies .
Similarly, thus far, the evidence for high-frequency jet ventilation is not superior to conventional ventilation for this population .
In the past, ventilator-dependent preterm neonates were often treated with glucocorticoids to prevent and treat BPD.
This differs from antenatal use, described in the next sections.
The American Academy of Pediatrics now recommends against routine neonatal corticosteroid use because of limited benefits and greater rates of impaired motor and cognitive function and school performance in exposed newborns .
The risk of adverse neurodevelopment is highest if dexamethasone is given to preterm newborns at low risk of BPD.
Attempts have been made to identify the highest-risk neonates for whom the benefits would exceed the risks .
Different types of corticosteroids, with various timing and administration routes, have been studied.
Current trials are focused on corticosteroids, mixed with surfactant, delivered intratracheally directly to the lung.
This approach may avoid some systemic adverse effects of corticosteroids .
In other efforts to prevent BPD, early animal studies demonstrated significant improvements in lung function with weeks of inhaled nitric oxide .
Despite initial enthusiasm, clinical trials failed to demonstrate a consistent benefit .
A National Institutes of Health (NIH)
consensus statement concluded that the available data do not support its use to prevent or treat BPD .
Caffeine has been used widely to treat apnea of prematurity, but it also has bronchodilatory effects.
One large randomized trial of caffeine versus placebo showed lower BPD rates, improved neurodevelopmental outcomes during early childhood, and good evidence of safety up to 11 years (Schmidt, 2006, 2012, 2017).
This therapy is now widely used for newborns weighing ≤1250 g.
The antioxidant vitamin A is necessary for normal lung growth and the integrity of respiratory tract epithelial cells.
Preterm newborns have low vitamin A levels at birth, and this is associated with a greater risk of developing BPD.
Randomized trials support the use of vitamin A to modestly reduce BPD rates for very-low-birthweight neonates weighing <1500 g .
Unfortunately, production shortages have limited the use of vitamin A prophylaxis in the past decade.
Surfactant Prophylaxis and Rescue Therapy Surfactant replacement was established decades ago as an effective and safe therapy for RDS. Surfactant improves mortality rates, reduces the need for ventilation, and improves short-term outcomes for low-birth-weight neonates .
It is standard therapy for newborn RDS .
Exogenous surfactant products are most commonly delivered via endotracheal tube to help treat RDS.
They contain biological or animal surfactants such as bovine—Survanta, calf—Infasurf, or porcine— Curosurf.
One Cochrane review found that animal-derived surfactants led to better outcomes than synthetic ones, which do not contain important surfactant proteins .
Currently, no synthetic surfactants are available, yet newer ones are in testing .
For rescue surfactant therapy, less invasive methods of delivery to spontaneously breathing preterm neonates have been developed.
These include surfactant application into the pharynx, surfactant nebulization, and application via laryngeal mask .
Administration of surfactant via a thin catheter while maintaining the newborn on CPAP is associated with reduced risk of death or BPD, lower intubation rate in the first 72 hours, reduced incidence of major complications, and a reduced inhospital mortality rate compared with administration via an endotracheal tube .
Surfactant has been used for prophylaxis of preterm, at-risk newborns.
Given together, antenatal corticosteroids and postnatal surfactant result in an even greater reduction in the overall death rate.
However, randomized trials indicate that in populations with high use of antenatal corticosteroids and routine use of CPAP in the delivery room, prophylactic surfactant is no longer beneficial and is associated with greater risk of death or BPD (RojasReyes, 2012; Sardesai, 2017).
# Prevention.
Antenatal Corticosteroids More than two decades ago, the NIH (2000) concluded that a single course of antenatal corticosteroid therapy reduces RDS and intraventricular hemorrhage rates in preterm neonates born between 24 and 34 weeks’ gestation (p. 619).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) considers all women at risk for preterm birth in this gestational-age range to be potential candidates for therapy.
It also may be considered for pregnant women starting at 23 weeks’ gestation who are at risk of preterm delivery within 7 days.
For the periviable fetus, other management guidelines are listed in Table 45-4 (p. 786).
Administration of corticosteroids for pregnant women during the periviable period who are at risk of preterm delivery within 7 days should be linked to a family’s decision regarding resuscitation and should be considered in that context.
Thus, as survival at even earlier gestations improves, the threshold for administration may decrease as well.
Administration of antenatal corticosteroids to women at risk for latepreterm delivery (34 to 36 weeks’ gestation) reduces the rate of neonatal respiratory complications .
Consideration of a single course of betamethasone for women at risk for late-preterm delivery is supported by the American College of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a).
Based on data presented in Chapter 45 (p. 802), at Parkland Hospital, this is not currently our practice.
Amniocentesis to Assess Fetal Lung Maturity Amniocentesis to assess fetal lung maturity was used previously to predict the neonatal risk for RDS.
However, this use of amniocentesis to guide delivery decisions in any clinical situation of pregnancy is not currently supported or recommended (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021a,b).
Necrotizing Enterocolitis.
This newborn bowel disorder has clinical findings that include abdominal distention, emesis, ileus, bilious gastric aspirates, and bloody stools.
Often, radiological images show pneumatosis intestinalis, which is bowel wall gas derived from invading bacteria .
Other classic imaging findings include hepatobiliary gas and pneumoperitoneum.
Bowel perforation necessitates prompt resection.
Figure 34-2.
Abdominal radiograph of a preterm newborn with necrotizing enterocolitis.
Note the distended air-filled loops of large and small bowel.
Significant pneumatosis intestinalis, which is intramural bowel gas, is visualized within the right lower quadrant and within the pelvis.
Not seen here, an associated finding is air in the portal veins of the liver.
Necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC) is seen primarily in low-birthweight newborns but occasionally in mature neonates.
Hypothesized causes include perinatal hypotension, hypoxia, sepsis, umbilical catheterization, exchange transfusions, blood transfusions, and the feeding of cow milk and hypertonic solutions .
The pathophysiology is thought to be multifactorial, and genetic disposition, intestinal immaturity, imbalance in microvascular tone, abnormal microbial colonization in the intestine, exposure to enteral feeds, and highly immunoreactive intestinal mucosa play potential roles (Bazacliu, 2019; Neu, 2011).
Medical treatment includes abdominal decompression, bowel rest, broad-spectrum antibiotics, and parenteral nutrition.
Surgery is reserved for neonates with intestinal perforation or deteriorating clinical or biochemical status.
Possible surgical procedures include drain placement, exploratory laparotomy with resection of diseased bowel, or enterostomy with creation of a stoma .
Retinopathy Of Prematurity.
By 1950, this condition, formerly known as retrolental fibroplasia, became the largest single cause of blindness in this country.
After the discovery that the disease resulted from hyperoxemia, its frequency declined but began to rise again with the increasing survival rates of extremely preterm newborns.
Normally, the fetal retina vascularizes centrifugally from the optic nerve starting at approximately the fourth month, and this continues until shortly after birth.
During vascularization, excessive oxygen induces severe retinal vasoconstriction, which leads to endothelial damage and vessel obliteration.
This is followed by subsequent aberrant neovascularization, in which the new vessels penetrate the retina and extend into the vitreous.
Here, they are prone to leak proteins or to burst and bleed.
Adhesions can form to detach the retina.
Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) contributes to normal angiogenesis and is upregulated during retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) development (Hellström, 2019).
This understanding has opened new avenues of treatment with anti-VEGF therapies.
The precise levels of hyperoxemia that can be sustained without causing ROP are unknown.
After birth, there is a “relative” hyperoxia compared with in-utero oxygen content, even in newborns not exposed to higher inspired oxygen concentrations.
To better understand the oxygen saturation threshold necessary to minimize ROP without raising rates of other adverse outcomes, the Neonatal Research Network performed a randomized trial of oxygenation in 1316 neonates born between 24 and 27 weeks’ gestation .
The two target ranges of oxygen saturation were 85 to 89 percent in one arm and 91 to 95 percent in the other arm.
These targets were both commonly employed in neonatal intensive
care units.
Death before discharge occurred significantly more frequently in the lower-oxygen saturation group—20 versus 16 percent.
However, severe ROP among survivors developed significantly less often in the lower-oxygen saturation group—8.6 versus 17.9 percent.
Brain Disorders.
Central nervous system injury usually creates different neuroanatomical sequelae in preterm newborns compared with those at term .
In preterm neonates, cerebral lesions detected by neuroimaging include intraventricular hemorrhage, cerebellar hemorrhage, periventricular hemorrhagic infarction, cystic periventricular leukomalacia, and diffuse white matter injury.
All of these are strongly associated with adverse neurodevelopmental outcomes .
Cranial sonography remains the preferred approach for detecting frequently occurring brain abnormalities and acute events in the preterm neonate.
It is readily available and reliable for detecting common abnormalities and monitoring brain growth.
Because cystic injuries may take 2 to 5 weeks to evolve, serial scans are obtained during this time.
In those whose findings are transient and resolve in the neonatal period, prognosis is improved compared with infants whose lesions remain and evolve.
At the same time, however, between 4 and 10 percent of prematurely born children may develop cerebral palsy (CP) in the absence of lesions.
Put another way, 90 to 96 percent of preterm newborns with CP have cerebral lesions that are detectable using cranial sonography.
# Intracranial Hemorrhage.
There are five major categories of intracranial hemorrhage in the neonate (Table 33-4, p. 607) .
Primary subarachnoid hemorrhage is more common in those born preterm and is frequently benign.
Cerebellar hemorrhage is also more frequent in preterm neonates and is increasingly recognized as a cause of serious sequelae.
Intraventricular hemorrhage (IVH) is almost exclusively seen in preterm newborns, is relatively common, and can have serious effects (Hintz, 2015, 2018).
Subdural hemorrhages are more frequent in term newborns and can be serious .
Miscellaneous intraparenchymal hemorrhage is also more frequent in those born at term and is of variable concern.
# Intraventricular Hemorrhage.
The germinal matrix is a highly cellular and vascular region of the developing brain located beneath the lateral ventricles.
In preterm neonates, the germinal matrix capillary network is fragile for several reasons.
First, the subependymal germinal matrix provides poor support for the vessels coursing through it.
Second, venous anatomy in this region causes stasis and congestion, which makes vessels susceptible to bursting if intravascular pressure rises.
Third, vascular autoregulation is impaired in the preterm neonate (Verhagen, 2014; Volpe, 2016).
If fragile capillaries in the germinal matrix rupture, blood escapes into the ventricular system—intraventricular hemorrhage (IVH).
This may dilate the ventricle, which then can obstruct venous drainage of the surrounding tissue.
As a result, venous infarction and hemorrhage, termed periventricular hemorrhagic infarction, may follow.
Risk of severe IVH is inversely related to gestational age .
IVH is a serious complication of preterm neonates born before 32 weeks and is particularly frequent in those born before 27 weeks.
The germinal matrix involutes between 34 and 36 weeks’ gestation.
Thus, IVH is infrequent after that period of brain development .
Most hemorrhages develop within 72 hours of birth .
Because IVH usually is recognized within 3 days of delivery, its genesis is sometimes erroneously attributed to birth events.
It is important to realize that prelabor IVH also can occur .
The pathogenesis of IVH is multifactorial and includes hypoxic-ischemic events, carbon dioxide elevations, anatomical factors, blood pressure instability, coagulopathy, genetic factors, and many others (Gilard, 2020; Leijser, 2019).
Moreover, preterm birth is frequently associated with infection, which further predisposes to endothelial activation, platelet adherence, and thrombi .
Respiratory distress and
mechanical ventilation are commonly associated factors .
Almost half of hemorrhages are clinically silent.
Most small germinal matrix hemorrhages and those confined to the cerebral ventricles resolve without impairment.
But, nearly half do show some sign of neurological impairment .
Survivors of extensive periventricular/intraventricular hemorrhage can have major neurodevelopmental handicaps .
Large lesions can result in hydrocephalus or in degenerated cystic areas termed periventricular leukomalacia (PVL), discussed later.
Importantly, the extent of PVL correlates with CP risk .
Incidence and Severity IVH incidences vary according to gestational age at birth.
Severe IVH rates have declined (Handley, 2018; Yeo, 2020).
From the Neonatal Research Network, the incidence from 1993 to 2012 for neonates <29 weeks’ gestation dropped from 19 to 13 percent .
In 2012, the incidence ranged from 11 percent in those born at 23 weeks to only 5 percent for those born at 28 weeks.
The severity of IVH can be assessed by neuroimaging studies.
Papile and coworkers (1978) devised the most widely used grading scheme to quantify the lesion extent and estimate prognosis.
Since the initial report, the Papile classification has been modified : • Grade I—hemorrhage is limited to the germinal matrix • Grade II—IVH occupies 10 to 50 percent of the ventricular area • Grade III—hemorrhage with >50 percent of the ventricular area involved • Parenchymal hemorrhage (previously called Grade IV)—most likely attributable to hemorrhagic venous infarction rather than extension of IVH into the parenchyma.
Antenatal Corticosteroids If given at least 48 hours before delivery, corticosteroids prevent or reduce the incidence of severe IVH .
A Consensus Development Conference of the NIH (1994) concluded that such therapy reduced rates of mortality, RDS, and IVH in preterm neonates born between 24 and 32 weeks’ gestation.
A second consensus statement by the NIH (2000) recommended that repeated courses of corticosteroids not be given .
Subsequently, the Maternal–Fetal Medicine Units Network reported that repeated corticosteroid courses were associated with some improved preterm neonatal outcomes, but also with reduced birthweight and increased risk for fetal-growth restriction .
Surveillance of this cohort through age 2 to 3 years found that children exposed to repeated versus single-dose corticosteroid courses did not differ significantly in physical or neurocognitive measures .
It was worrisome, however, that infants exposed to multiple courses had a nonsignificant 5.7-fold relative risk of CP.
At the same time, the 2-year follow-up of the Australian Collaborative Trial was reported by Crowther and coworkers (2007).
In more than 1100 newborns, the incidence of CP was almost identical—4.2 versus 4.8 percent —in those given repeated versus single-course corticosteroids, respectively.
More recently, it was reported that for those born before 28 weeks’ gestation, if 10 days or more had passed since betamethasone administration, the incidence of severe IVH was higher .
This is not a consistent finding in all studies .
The most recent recommendations from the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) are for a single course of corticosteroids for pregnant women between 240/7 weeks and 336/7 weeks’ gestation who are at risk for preterm delivery.
They further note that those given their initial course more than 14 days prior and who have imminent risk of preterm delivery may receive a second “rescue” course.
Other Preventive Methods Although antenatal magnesium sulfate for those at risk for preterm delivery does not reduce the incidence of IVH, it does offer protection from neurodevelopmental impairment .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends its use for this indication, as discussed further in Chapter 45 (p. 803).
Antenatal vitamin K and phenobarbital and postnatal phenobarbital have not consistently reduced the incidence of IVH in studies (Crowther, 2010a,b; Smit, 2013).
Although vitamin E reduced IVH rates, the associated risk for sepsis was increased .
Metaanalyses of the many randomized trials of postnatal indomethacin and other prostaglandin inhibitors show inconsistent results regarding reductions in IVH rates (Fowlie, 2010; Mitra, 2018).
None has shown improvements in neurodevelopmental impairment.
The benefits of cesarean delivery compared with vaginal birth to lower IVH rates remains controversial.
One metaanalysis reported that cesarean delivery for very-low-birthweight neonates had no effect on rates of severe IVH but did reduce overall IVH rates .
The benefits of cesarean delivery to lower IVH rates in breech and growth-restricted fetuses are unclear from current observational data .
Prospective trials are needed.
Delayed umbilical cord clamping compared to immediate cord clamping has been reported to reduce the risk for any grade of IVH in preterm newborns but has not reduced rates of severe IVH (Rabe, 2019; Seidler, 2021).
In preterm neonates, deferred cord clamping may also raise hemoglobin and hematocrit levels and improve survival rates .
Cord milking is associated with higher rates of severe IVH in neonates <28 weeks’ gestation and should be avoided (Katheria, 2019; Wyckoff, 2020).
# Periventricular Leukomalacia.
This histological description refers to cystic areas deep in brain white matter that develop after hemorrhagic or ischemic infarction.
Tissue ischemia leads to regional necrosis.
Because brain tissue does not regenerate and the preterm neonate has minimal gliosis, these irreversibly damaged areas appear as echolucent cysts in neuroimaging studies.
Generally, they require at least 2 weeks to form but may develop as late as 4 months after the initial insult.
Thus, their presence at birth may help to determine the timing of an inciting event.
Cerebral Palsy.
This group of conditions is characterized by chronic movement or posture abnormalities that are cerebral in origin, arise early in life, and are nonprogressive .
Epilepsy and mental retardation frequently accompany CP.
Its cause differs in preterm and term neonates, and the latter is described in Chapter 33 (p. 602).
CP is commonly classified by the type of neurological dysfunction— spastic, dyskinetic, or ataxic—and by the number and distribution of limbs involved—quadriplegia, diplegia, hemiplegia, or monoplegia.
Spastic quadriplegia has a strong association with developmental retardation and epilepsy.
Spastic quadriplegia is the most severe form of spastic CP and affects all four limbs, the trunk, and the face.
Spastic diplegia is common in preterm or low-birthweight neonates.
In this CP type, muscle stiffness is mainly in the legs, and the arms are less or not involved.
Affected persons might have difficulty walking because tight extremity muscles cause their legs to pull together, turn inward, and cross at the knees.
Spastic hemiplegia affects only one side of a person’s body, and the arm is affected usually more than the leg.
Dyskinetic CP includes athetoid, choreoathetoid, and dystonic cerebral forms.
Poor control of hand, arm, feet, and leg movements make sitting and walking difficult.
Movements may be slow and writhing or rapid and jerky.
Ataxic CP manifests as problems with balance and coordination.
Mixed CP manifests with symptoms of more than one CP type.
The most common type is spastic–dyskinetic CP .
# Incidence.
According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2020a), the prevalence of CP in the United States approximates 3 cases in 1000 children.
Hafström and coworkers (2018) reported the 6-year follow-up of all babies born at gestational ages <28 weeks in Sweden from 2004 to 2007.
The CP rate overall was 10.5 percent, and no linear association was found between gestational age at birth and CP rates in this cohort.
# Risks.
Intraventricular Hemorrhage Various clinical and pathological data link CP with associated severe IVH (grade III or IV) and resulting PVL.
Low-grade IVH is generally considered benign, but it is associated with higher
rates of CP in school-aged children born extremely preterm .
Higher IVH grades are associated with even greater rates.
Ischemia Preterm newborns are susceptible to brain ischemia and PVL.
This is in part due to immature cerebral vasculature and an immature cerebrovascular autoregulation system that is pressure passive.
In response to systemic hypotension, preterm infants cannot increase cerebral perfusion to borderzone regions of the brain supplied by the immature penetrating cerebral vasculature .
This triggers a cascade of events caused by hypoxia–ischemia that results in pyramidal tract damage, which can cause spastic diplegia.
Perinatal Infection/Inflammation PVL is associated with infection and inflammation.
In one study of 753 neonates born between 24 and 32 weeks’ gestation, 9 percent developed PVL .
Those born before 28 weeks, those who had inflammatory events during the last days to weeks before delivery, and those who had both were at highest risk.
In another study, PVL was strongly associated with prolonged membrane rupture, chorioamnionitis, and neonatal hypotension .
Bailis and coworkers (2008) reported that chronic—and not acute—placental inflammation was associated with PVL.
In another study of 3094 singletons born before 33 weeks’ gestation, 15 percent had evidence of clinical chorioamnionitis .
Compared with noninfected infants, cases complicated by infection had significantly higher rates of IVH—22 versus 12 percent.
Fetal infection may be a key element in the pathway between preterm birth and CP (Burd, 2012; Leviton, 2010, Novack, 2018).
As discussed in Chapter 45 (p. 789), chorioamnionitis is a major cause of spontaneous preterm delivery.
In the pathway proposed in Figure 34-3, antenatal reproductive tract infection evokes the production of cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF) and interleukins 1, 6, and 8.
These in turn stimulate prostaglandin production and preterm labor.
Preterm fetal intracranial blood vessels are susceptible to rupture and damage, and the cytokines that stimulate preterm labor also have direct toxic effects on oligodendrocytes and myelin.
Vessel rupture, tissue hypoxia, and cytokine-mediated damage result in massive neuronal cell death.
Glutamate is released, which stimulates membrane receptors to allow excess calcium to enter the neurons.
High intracellular calcium levels are toxic to white matter, and glutamate may be directly toxic to oligodendrocytes .
Inflammation induced by the activation of microglia and macrophages with the production and release of proinflammatory cytokines, chemokines, proteases, complement factors, excitotoxic amino acids, reactive oxygen species, and nitric oxide further exacerbates secondary brain injury .
Figure 34-3.
Schematic representation of the hypothesized pathway between maternal or intrauterine infection and preterm birth or periventricular leukomalacia.
Both potentially lead to cerebral palsy.
LPS = lipopolysaccharide; PG = prostaglandin.
Many studies show that infection and cytokines can directly damage the immature brain (Chau, 2014; Yoon, 1997a).
TNF and interleukin 6 were more frequently found in the brains of infants who died with PVL .
Cytokines are strongly linked to white matter lesions even when organisms cannot be demonstrated .
# Prevention—Neuroprotection.
The benefits of antenatal magnesium sulfate and corticosteroids are well described .
Another potential neuroprotective therapy is erythropoiesis-stimulating agents (ESAs) such as erythropoietin and darbepoetin.
In addition to stimulating erythropoiesis, ESAs protect the developing brain in animal models .
One recent metaanalysis found decreased rates of IVH and PVL in preterm neonates treated with ESAs soon after birth.
The effects on neurodevelopmental impairment are unclear .
In one large trial, early high-dose erythropoietin compared with placebo did not lower the risk of severe neurodevelopmental impairment or death at age 2 years .
A large trial of the longeracting darbepoetin has completed enrollment and is in the follow-up phase
clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01471015).
Last, discussed in Chapter 33 (p. 602) for neonates >36 weeks, induced hypothermia for neuroprotection is not recommended for preterm newborns.
This stems from their different pattern of gray and white matter injury and their greater susceptibility to cold stress.
The exact gestational age for which therapeutic cooling for hypoxicischemic encephalopathy (HIE) would provide more benefit than harm is unknown.
A trial of cooling for neonates born at 330/7 to 356/7 weeks’ gestation with moderate/severe HIE has completed enrollment and is in the follow-up phase.